בוקר טוב. Boker tov. All right, so happy sixth day of חנוכה
Chanukah and ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. First day of ראש חודש. Rosh
Chodesh. Today's דף daf is דף כ, daf chaf, 20, and we
begin the new פרק. perek. We begin finally moving from the whole
issue about טמא tamei and entering into the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
to the issue of שבועות, Shvuot, which is the focus of our
מסכת. Masechet. The first focus is the issue of the קרבן, Korban,
because that was at least the way the connection to the idea
of two that is four, and when do you bring a קרבן
Korban of עולה ויורד Oleh Ve-yored when you make an oath and
then you don't fulfill it and so on. But eventually we are
going to get into the reason this is in סדר נזיקין Seder
Nezikin and the use of oaths in a court context. But anyway
we begin here at the bottom of יט עמוד ב. Yud Tet
Amud Bet. We'll reread the משנה Mishna we read at the end
of yesterday. We'll reread it again today, or we'll reread it today.
שבועות שתים שהן ארבע. Shvuot shtayim she-hein arba. There are two which
are four, in cases of that you would bring a קרבן. Korban.
This is based on the פסוקים Psukim that says, נפש כי תשבע
לבטא בשפתים להרע או להיטיב, Nefesh ki tishava levate bisfatayim lehara o
le-heitiv,
to do bad or to do good, which is understood to mean
translated very abstractly, to do bad means you won't eat something, that's,
you know, bad to your body, to do good is you will
eat something, again maybe depends if you're dieting or what it is
you're trying to not eat or to eat anyway. So those are
the two, and then you transgress that, that's a קרבן. Korban. Or,
that's the two and the four is if you make an oath
about the past, what you did do or you didn't do, something
in the past, and that would be the four, and that would
also be a קרבן, Korban, okay, if you did if you were
swearing falsely. We'll get to the whole issue about wittingly or unwittingly
and so on. Okay, so שבועה שאוכל ושלא אוכל, Shvua she-ochel veshelo
ochel, that's the two of the future that are in the פסוקים.
Psukim. שאכלתי ושלא אכלתי, She-achalti veshelo achalti,
that I did eat and I didn't eat, those are the two
that are past-oriented. שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל כל שהוא חייב דברי רבי
עקיבא. Shvua shelo ochel ve-achal kol shehu chayav divrei Rabbi Akiva.
Now let's talk about that שבועה. Shvua. You make an oath that
you won't eat. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says even if you
eat the smallest amount you're חייב. chayav. אמרו לו לרבי עקיבא, Amru
lo le-Rabbi Akiva, they say to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, היכן מצינו
באוכל בכל שהוא שהוא חייב? heichan matzinu be-ochel be-chol shehu shehu chayav?
When do you ever find, again by the way חייב chayav here
probably means חייב chayav in the context of a קרבן, Korban, you
might by the way remember the whole position in מכות Makkot about
the that even a כל שהוא, kol shehu, I think it was
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, whoever it was, that said that even a
small amount you would be חייב. chayav. But anyway we'll bracket that,
but it is interesting that those are parallel issues debated in the
משנה. Mishna. But they say to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, when do you ever find that the eating of the
smallest amount you are חייב? chayav? You normally need a כזית. kezayit.
And again, presumably we're talking in the context of a קרבן, Korban,
which will be made explicit at the end. So normally, but anyway,
you normally need a כזית kezayit whether for a קרבן Korban or
for מלקות. Malkot. How do you say here even the smallest amount?
אמר להם רבי עקיבא, Amar lahem Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
said back to them, וכהיכן מצינו במדבר מביא קרבן? u-khe-heichan matzinu be-medaber
mevi korban? Where do you find somebody bring a קרבן Korban just
for a speech act? You know, this person just said something. Now
of course he said and then he acted, he said he won't
eat and he did actively eat, but so maybe you could focus
on the action, but ultimately the קרבן Korban is for violating the
שבועה, Shvua, the words that come out of your mouth. Not only
that, if you say you will eat and you won't eat, so
then you didn't do anything, you were passive and it's all about
the oath. Or since there are two that are four, if you
take an oath about the past, clearly that's a קרבן Korban just
for your words. So when do we ever find a קרבן Korban
just for your words? So therefore, שזה מדבר מביא קרבן. she-ze medaber
mevi korban. Now okay, very nice, so you bring a קרבן Korban
for your words. What does it have to do with bringing a
קרבן Korban for eating even the smallest amount? What does it have
to do with the amount? רש"י Rashi says since this is rooted
in your words,
we therefore try to focus on what did you mean by your
words. And you know, you could have said I'm not going to
eat like, I don't know, like two gallons, drink two gallons of
something. You could define, it's not like it's a מצוה mitzvah in
the תורה Torah that the תורה Torah defines the amount, that the
prohibited amount is a כזית. kezayit. Since this is all based on
formulating what you said with your words, you could say I'm not
going to eat the smallest amount, I'm not going to eat 20
pounds of something. So therefore, since the way רש"י Rashi explains, since
this is rooted in your words, we assume that if you just
said I'm not going to eat, what you meant was eat even
the smallest amount. רש"י Rashi says the meaning of the response to
say that this focuses on your words, this is not a forbidden
food that you ate, this is a violation of your oath, and
therefore we will interpret or assume that if you don't specify, you
mean even the smallest amount. All right, we'll get back to that
later and see if there's other ways of understanding his linking of
the idea of the focus on violating your words with the idea
of the smallest amount and not having a minimum size. Let's take
a look though at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara doesn't focus
on that at all initially. It focuses more generally on the issue
of making a שבועה. Shvua. So let's take a look. למימרא L'meymra
says the גמרא, Gemara, this implies, דכי שאוכל דאכילה משמע. de-ki she-ochel
d'achila mashma.
When you say a שבועה Shvua that I will eat, אוכל ochel
means I will eat. Okay, what else could it mean? Okay, ורמינהי,
u-re-minei, but wait, I'll show you. We've got a case where where
what do you call it? We've got a case where it sounds
like in נדרים, Nedarim, where it sounds like שאוכל she-ochel means I
won't eat. Okay, if somebody takes an oath and says the
following: שבועה לא אוכל לך. Shvua lo ochel lach. Now, so there,
the meaning is because of the context and this is what the
גמרא Gemara is going to say, that it's all about context. If
I say an oath that I will eat anything of yours means
an oath that I won't eat anything of yours in that context.
Like, I will have violated my oath if I will eat anything
of yours. Okay, so so so that or, wait, רש״י Rashi says
maybe I will yes, so or לא שבועה שלא אוכל לך, Lo
shevuah shelo ochal lach, it would be not a violation of my
oath if I didn't eat anything of yours, which is like a
double negative. So it will be a violation of my oath if
I do eat something of yours. Okay, but anyway, so if you
remove the double negative, again it's שבועה אוכל לך Shevuah ochal lach
where we're reading it not to be an oath that I will,
I'm taking an oath that I will, but we're reading it it'll
be a violation of my oath if I will eat. Okay, so
how do you know? Does שבועה אוכל לך Shevuah ochal lach mean
I'm taking an oath that I will eat, or does it mean
that I am forbidding myself with an oath that I should, you
know, and that I will have transgressed my שבועה shevuah if I
eat something of yours? So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye
says, אסור, assur, in all those cases forbidden. אמר אביי לעולם דאכילנא
לך, Amar Abaye le'olam de-achilna lach, yes, אוכל ochal means I will
eat. But לא קשיא כאן דמסרבין בו לאכול כאן דאין מסרבין בו
לאכול, lo kashya kan de-misarvin bo le-echol kan de-ein misarvin bo le-echol,
it's all about context. Are you trying to pressure me to eat
and I'm taking an oath to push back on that pressure? You're
like, "Come on, have a little, what's the big deal, come on,
you know, be a good be a you know be a pal,
just have some." No, שבועה שאוכל לך. Shevuah she-ochal lach. So that
means in that context clearly I am pushing back against your trying
to pressure me to eat and שבועה שאוכל Shevuah she-ochal means I
will have I will violate my oath or I'm forbidden in an
oath and that that will be a violation if I were to
eat, you know, if I were to eat לך lach from you.
Okay. מתניתין בשאין מסרבין בו לאכול, Mattnitin be-she-ein misarvin bo le-echol,
when you're not pressuring me and I just come up to you
and I say שבועה שאוכל לך, Shevuah she-ochal lach, so we translate
that normally without any particular context, it means an oath that I
will eat. That's the simple meaning of the words. But ברייתא במסרבין
בו לאכול, Braisa be-misarvin bo le-echol, the ברייתא Braisa is when you're
pressuring the guy to eat and there שבועה שאוכל Shevuah she-ochal means
I'm taking an oath that I won't eat, or it'll be a
violation of my oath, you know, I'm bound by an oath were
I to eat from you that would you know against eating from
you. Okay, so that's what the context means. דקאמר לא אכילנא ולא
אכילנא, De-ka'amar lo achilna ve-lo achilna, and you're and the guy's saying
you say eat, eat, I say no, no and you keep on
pressuring
me דכי קא משתבע הכי קאמר שבועה שלא אוכל לך. de-ki ka
mishtava hachi ka'amar shevuah shelo ochal lach. So when he says שבועה
שאוכל Shevuah she-ochal it means שלא אוכל, shelo ochal, which you totally
get, right? That in that context, that's what it means. An oath
were I to eat from you.
It's like that famous line they say from what's his name, Stanley
Morgenbecher, is that his name? Morgenbesser, you know this guy? He was
this brilliant guy, I think Columbia University, anyway, like you know he
was known for like say like like these like one-liners, you know,
able like to puncture you know what somebody was saying. Anyway, apparently
there was a whole lecture and the guy was up in the
lecture and the guy was sort of saying something like, you know,
it's very strange because like a double negative is a positive but
a double positive isn't a negative. So then he pipes up from
the audience and says, "Yeah, yeah." So anyway, so sometimes yes means
no, you know, it all depends on the context. Okay. So alright,
so that's what אביי Abaye says. רב אשי אמר תני שבועה שאי
אוכל לך. Rav Ashi amar tani shevuah she-ee ochal lach. The ברייתא,
Braisa,
what we quoted,
you know actually
whether it's a ברייתא Braisa or משנה Mishnah actually it's a variation
but the ברייתא Braisa משנה Mishnah we quoted that you say שבועה
שאוכל לך Shevuah she-ochal lach means I won't eat, he actually says
that's actually a you know an abbreviated, not abbreviated, what's it called,
a you like anyway what's it called when you sort of like
combine two
words? Conjunction? Contraction. It's almost like a contracted type of statement. שאוכל
She-ochal means שאי אוכל. she-ee ochal. It works because it starts with
an א, alef, right? So שבועה שאוכל Shevuah she-ochal in that way
you actually what you didn't hear is that it was שאי אוכל
לך. she-ee ochal lach. Okay and that sounds like שאוכל she-ochal but
he actually said I won't eat. Okay, actually you get this a
lot in, you know, it's been a while since we did ירושלמי
Yerushalmi but like in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi for example you get like
a ל lamed sometimes which is like לא la
something like לא אכילנא, la achilna, לא אכילנא la achilna
right, which actually equals לא אוכילנא, lo ochilna, right? So the ל
lamed sort of becomes the לא. lo. Okay, so anyway he's saying
שאוכל she-ochal is שאי אוכל לך. she-ee ochal lach. Okay, so רב
אשי אמר
תני שבועה שאי אוכל לך. Rav Ashi amar tani shevuah she-ee ochal
lach. You have to add in the word that I won't in
that previous ברייתא. Braisa. So גמרא Gemara says אי הכי מאי למימרא,
ee hachi mai lemeimra, so then it's obvious and there's no חידוש
chiddush of that whole thing because you explicitly He said you won't
eat. So no, מהו דתימא mahu d'teima לישנא דאיתקלי, lishna d'itkilei, maybe
I would think that he said שאי, she'i, but he didn't mean
to say שאי, she'i, he meant to say he will eat. קא
משמע לן kamashmalan that if you said שאי אוכל, she'i ochel, you
mean שאי אוכל. she'i ochel. Okay, so it sounds like a cheap
answer, the רב אשי Rav Ashi answer, but it could be actually
correct, like because especially again in like Mishnaic Hebrew, Palestinian Hebrew, and
so on, you have contractions like that where "won't" sort of glides
into the word, and שאי אוכל, she'i ochel, you could see how
that becomes שאוכל, she'ochel, right? You could sort of see how that
you sort of lose the hearing that distinctive prefix there. Okay, so
that's dealing with that ברייתא. Braita.
Takes it out of the context though.
Right, so then that becomes a question: Is אביי Abaye really arguing
with—is רב אשי Rav Ashi arguing with אביי? Abaye? Is רב אשי
Rav Ashi saying you ignore context? Presumably not, he's just saying you
don't have to interpret the ברייתא Braita that way. Since the ברייתא
Braita didn't give you that context, it's not fair to assume that
context. But right, it doesn't seem like you could say that they're
arguing הלכה. halakhically. Does context matter? But when you learn enough like
נדרים Nedarim and שבועות, Shavuot, you see that this is one area
where we really do want to not just understand purely formalistically the
words that came out of your mouth, but what you were meaning
or what you were getting at, right? So the issue of פיו
ולבו שוין, piv v'libo shavin, it's not just what you said, it's
what you intended. So it doesn't—it would not seem to me that
he's arguing as a matter of הלכה, halakha, just as a matter
of interpretation. But you're right, that's a question to ask. Okay, תנו
רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So now we're going to get to what language
makes up something constituting a שבועה. shvua. And like I said at
the outset, and there's a ר"ן Ran in the beginning of נדרים
Nedarim that talks about this, you know, that a classic שבועה shvua
is to take an oath in the name of God. Right, לא
תשבעו בשמי לשקר, lo tishav'u bishmi lashaker, right? So, you know, you
know, בי נשבעתי, bi nishbati, even God swears, God swears in God's
own name, right? I'm serious, בי נשבעתי נאם ה'. bi nishbati neum
Hashem. So there's one interesting question which is if when you say
a שבועה shvua to violate the prohibition of like, you know, לא
תשא שם ה' אלהיך לשוא lo tisa shem Hashem elokecha lashav or
whatever you violate when you take an oath, you know, does it
have to be with God's name or not? And there's an interesting
debate in the ראשונים Rishonim about that. When you don't say God's
name but somebody just says שבועה אוכל לך shvua ochel lach like
we saw, is God's name implied? Is every שבועה shvua only הלכה
halakhically a שבועה shvua because it implies God's name? There's a principle
in שבועות Shavuot and נדרים Nedarim called a יד, yad, a יד
yad is a handle, okay, but what a יד yad means is
sort of that like you don't always spell out exactly what you're
saying, but it's implicit in your words and you're like dot dot
dot, like it's a handle towards something else, okay, so maybe one
way of understanding it is that every שבועה shvua is only הלכה
halakhically a שבועה shvua because God's name is implied. So that's one
question which doesn't—we don't start with here, but I just wanted to
sort of put that issue up front, the question of God's name
in a שבועה. shvua. That's not like a נדר. neder. A נדר
neder more works like establishing the status of thing, like I say,
"this will be like a קרבן." korban. You know, you don't need
to invoke God's name for that, right? It's just creating a status
as opposed to the idea of a שבועה shvua is that you
call upon God to witness something. So that's one general question about
how much does a שבועה shvua imply or, you know, require God's
name. But now we're going to get to a question about what's
the line between when are you saying a שבועה shvua and when
are you sort of saying like, "I promise," right? So, you know,
I mean we have technical words: I swear, I take an oath,
right, you know, so, you know, let's say somebody says "on my
mother's grave" which is, you know, or something like that. When does
something become a שבועה, shvua, right? What is the technical word that
draws the line between a שבועה shvua and a, you know, and
just a promise or an assertion? So let's take a look. תנו
רבנן: tanu rabbanan: מבטא, שבועה. Mifta shvuah. This is based on the
language of the פסוק, pasuk, when the פסוק pasuk speaks about taking
an oath, it says, you know, כי נפש כי תשבע לבטא בשפתים.
ki nefesh ki tishava l'vatei bisfatayim. This is the verse by bringing
the קרבן korban if the person swears and then violates it.
So the word מבטא mivta, becomes now a technical word which means
to enunciate, right? If I just said in English, "I'm enunciating," you
know, אני מפרש, ani mevaresh, right, if you said it in Hebrew,
it doesn't matter, it's not the meaning of the word, it becomes
a technical word. So now if somebody says "מבטא mivta that I
will eat from you, you know, מבטא mivta that I'm going to
go to the ball game tonight or something like that," so that's
like saying שבועה. shvua. That's a technical word now that means I'm
taking an oath. Okay, so מבטא mivta is a שבועה. shvua. איסר,
issar, שבועה. shvua. Now let's say somebody said, "forbidden," now that's also
based on the verse: לאסור איסר על נפשו, le'esor issar al nafsho,
to make something forbidden on himself. So that's a little funnier cause
איסר issar seems to be like a pretty generic word, right? But
if somebody says "איסר, issar, this I won't eat from this—from this
loaf of bread," presumably איסר issar is only a word that works
if you're saying you're not going to do something, something is forbidden
to you. It would be funny to say "איסר issar I'm going
to go to the ball game today," okay? But "איסר issar I
won't eat from this loaf of bread," that's also a technical word
that means a שבועה. shvua. Okay, איסר, issar, and based on the
verse, שבועה. shvua. איסר איסר. Isar isar. Now, the nature of the
prohibited nature of an איסר, Isar, אם אתה אומר איסר שבועה חייב.
im ata omer Isar shevua chayav. If you say איסר Isar constitutes
a שבועה, shvua. you're חייב. chayav. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, but if
איסר Isar doesn't constitute a שבועה, shevua, פטור, patur, you're exempt. So
the גמרא Gemara says, Ha? אם
אתה אומר איסר שבועה, im ata omer Isar shevua, if you say
איסר Isar constitutes a שבועה, shevua, ואמרת איסר שבועה הוא, ve'amarta Isar
shevua hu, you first said איסר Isar is a שבועה, shevua, then
right after you said, oh if it's a שבועה shevua, then this
and if not then this. Make up your mind. So אמר אביי
הכי קאמר, amar Abaye hachi ka'amar, here's how to read it. Now
this whole debate, רש"י Rashi tells us how to read what אביי
Abaye is saying. I'm going to read it תוספות's Tosafot way. Okay,
here's what it means.
מבטא mivta is a שבועה. shevua איסר, Isar, if you say
איסר, Isar, מתפס בשבועה. mitpas bishvua. That's when you... now התפסה hatfasa
is the following.
התפסה בנדר hatfasa bi'neder is the following. If I say this thing
is קרבן, korban, קונם, konam, this is אסור assur like a קרבן.
korban. And then I say about this thing, זה כזה. zeh kazeh.
This is like this. So that's מתפס, mitpas, I'm grabbing it on
and I'm transferring status. Okay, A is like B. Now that works
a lot when you're talking about status. I'm associating this with that.
Okay, if I see a נזיר nazir walking in front of me
and I say הריני כזה hareni kazeh or הריני כמהו, hareni kamoho,
and you know, and that's מתפס. mitpas. I'm like, it's like grabbing
my status onto his. Okay, and through that association I'm like sort
of applying the same status to me or to this object or
whatever. Okay, מתפס בשבועה mitpas bishvua is a little different because here's
a very critical point to understand everything we're learning today, and I
said it before but you have to always repeat it. A נדר
neder is about an object. It sort of works by the same
way you can make a קרבן. korban. A שבועה shevua. is about
an action, either doing or not doing, and it's more about calling
upon God to witness, you know, the truth, the veracity of your
statement, of your claim, or to hold you responsible to live up
to your promise. Okay, that's what a שבועה shevua is. It's action
and person-based, not object-based. Okay, so what would be מתפס mitpas of
a שבועה? shevua So מתפס mitpas of a שבועה shevua? would be
that I would say, if somebody would say a שבועה shevua that
he won't eat, you know, we'll call this an apple. A שבועה
shevua he won't eat this apple, okay, and then he takes this
apple and he doesn't say זה כזה zeh kazeh because it's not
really about the apple, it's really about me, right? So what I
would say is, you know, I am אסור assur in this apple.
So I talk about me, not the apple. I am אסור assur
in this apple just like in this one. So what I am
sort of... I by saying I can't eat this just like I
can't eat that, I'm grabbing on abstractly to my שבועה. shevua What
I'm somewhat implying is, a similarly a שבועה shevua. should bind me
not to eat this. But it's very indirect, right? I'm אסור assur
in this like I'm אסור assur in that, right?
This already has an איסור. issur.
Yeah, I first say a שבועה shevua that I won't eat this
apple, and then I say, and an איסר Isar this is on
me, איסר Isar I won't eat this one just like I won't
eat that one. Okay. And does that make... since I used the
word איסר, Isar, which is now the technical word, and I'm associating
it with a שבועה, shevua does that now become like a שבועה?
shevua, Okay.
So that's the case. I just want to double check תוספות Tosafot
to make sure I'm saying this right, one second.
Hold on.
Yes. Okay. Okay, so now let's continue. Okay, so איסר Isar is
the scenario of an איסר Isar is מתפס בשבועה. mitpas bishvua. I
say I won't eat this just like I won't eat that. איסר
Isar that I won't eat this, okay, that just like I won't
eat that.
Or maybe... okay, or maybe I don't even use the technical word
איסר. Isar. I'm sorry, תוספות Tosafot might say that it's just describing
a scenario, right, to say it more accurately. When the תורה Torah
says לאסור איסר על נפשו, le'esor issar al nafsho, what it means
is it's describing a scenario where somebody basically doesn't say a שבועה
shevua? I won't eat something or מבטא Mifta I won't eat something,
מבטא's mifta the language of a שבועה, shevua but says I won't
eat this just like I won't eat that. And he's sort of
piggybacking on a pre-existing שבועה. shevua, That's what the word איסר Isar
refers to in the תורה. Torah. Now, okay, so let's keep on
going. מבטא mifta שבועה, shevua. איסר Isar מתפס בשבועה. mitpas bishvua. איסר
איסר. Isar isar. Now, what is the nature of when you grab
onto a שבועה? shevua, Okay. So he says it depends on the
context. אם אתה אומר מתפס בשבועה כמוציא שבועה מפיו דמי וחייב. im
ata omer mitpas bishvua kemotzi shevua mipiv dami vechayav. ואם לאו פטור.
ve'im lav patur. So תוספות Tosafot adds in the word וחייב. vechayav.
The way תוספות Tosafot reads it is the following. Okay let me
just double check תוספות Tosafot one more second.
Okay, so תוספות Tosafot has it like this. If I do an
איסר, Isar, this is the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, this is
a little complicated, then I'm going to do another way תוספות Tosafot
reads it which is even better, but let's start with this way.
Okay. So the scenario of איסר... Isar... So if I say this
is like this. Now, is does that have the weight of a
שבועה? shevua? Well, it depends what I do. If I do it
like I am saying a שבועה. shvuah? Like what it means like
I'm saying a שבועה shvuah. is I'm saying this thing is forbidden
to me, that would be just like saying a שבועה. shvuah Except
when I say a שבועה shvuah. I say שבועה shvuah this thing
is forbidden to me. But if I do it like I'm saying
a שבועה, shvuah כהוציא שבועה מפיו דמי, kimotzi shvuah mipiv dami, but
I do it by saying this thing is אסור asur to me
like this. Okay, so but I basically sort of say like, you
know, this thing is אסור asur to me. I use the language
I use for a שבועה. shvuah, I focus on like my, you
know, or rather saying, I'm sorry, less that I say this thing,
which is but I won't eat this, excuse me, I won't eat
this like this, which is a שבועה shvuah. type of a language.
I'm talking about my action, I won't eat this. So if I
do it כהוציא שבועה מפיו דמי, kimotzi shvuah mipiv dami, the same
way I would take a שבועה shvuah and then it is forbidden.
Okay, if, however, I don't say I won't eat it, I just
say this is like this, which focuses on the object, then it's
not really a שבועה shvuah and then it's not really forbidden. So
let me write this out because I figure I think I might
have lost you and myself with this. It's complicated because you know
רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos disagree. I'm going to give you another
read of תוספות Tosfos which is more elegant but anyway. So all
of this turns on the first one being a real שבועה.
shvuah Right, so the word איסור issur itself would not be a
שבועה. shvuah.
Right, according to תוספות, Tosfos, it's not really that using the word
איסור issur as a technical word, it's really about describing a scenario.
מתפס. mispas. Okay, right. Exactly. So here's the guy, okay? You like
my picture of a guy? And here's his apple, okay? Okay, here's
apple number one and here's apple number two, okay? So if this
guy says מבטא Mifta
I won't eat, that's the first point, okay? That's a שבועה. shvuah.
Okay, now, whatever he said about apple number one, okay, now he
comes over to apple number two. So if he says,
I
won't eat number two like number one, okay? So that's
מתפס mispas and that's כהוציא שבועה מפיו
kimotzi shvuah
mipiv because he said I won't eat, which is language of a
שבועה, shvuah. okay? And therefore it is חייב. chayav. If he does
it in a way that is like saying a שבועה, shvuah, okay,
then it is like he said a שבועה, shvuah, even though he
doesn't use any technical term, okay? That's scenario number. If, however, he
says number two is like number one, okay, and he doesn't use
the מוציא, motzi, the language of a שבועה, shvuah, the language of
a שבועה shvuah, focuses on your action, then you are פטור, patur,
it is not a שבועה shvuah language. So basically the point of
this is מתפס mispas is when you do a התפסה, hatfasah, it
is like you took a שבועה shvuah if you include the language
that focuses on your action. So I won't eat is just a
promise, you need a technical term. What's the technical term? מבטא mifta
would be a technical term, שבועה shvuah would be a technical term,
and מתפס mispas
if you have the language of I won't eat, this becomes because
of the piggybacking that substitutes the role of the technical term. That's
like if you said שבועה shvuah I won't eat. I won't eat
number two like number one, you understand, because you have the I
won't eat,
the connecting of number two to number one is like you said
שבועה shvuah I won't eat. But if you didn't have the I
won't eat, if you just had number two is like number one,
it would not be a שבועה shvuah language. All right, that's the
way תוספות Tosfos reads the ברייתא. baraisa. Let me just reread that
in the גמרא Gemara make sure we've got that, then I'll take
the question. אמר אביי הכי קאמר: Amar Abaye hachi ka'amar: מבטא mifta
שבועה. shvuah איסור, Issur, now, again, the way תוספות Tosfos reads this
you do not use the term איסור issur here, it just means
when the תורה Torah talks about איסר, issar, it what it's describing
is a scenario of מתפס בשבועה. mispas bishvuah. So the איסור issur
in the תורה Torah is
מתפס בשבועה. mispas bishvuah. So now, then the ברייתא baraisa goes on,
is doing a התפסה hatfasah does that count like a שבועה shvuah
or not? It depends what else you said in addition to the
number two is number one. Okay, אם אתה אומר מתפס בשבועה כהוציא
שבועה מפיו דמי, im ata omer mispas bishvuah kimotzi shvuah mipiv dami,
if you do a מתפס בשבועה mispas bishvuah by doing it like
you said the actual שבועה shvuah by saying the I won't eat
phrase, then וחייב, vechayav, then you would be חייב, chayav, okay? ואם
לאו, veim lav,
but if you didn't do it with the phrase of I won't
eat you just did the התפסה, hatfasah, then פטור patur you would
be exempt, okay? So that's the way at least תוספות Tosfos reads
that, רש״י Rashi reads it in a different way. This is not
about using the technical term of איסור. issur. Now I wanted to
tell you a different read of תוספות Tosfos which I really like
because it's an easier read of the language of the גמרא, Gemara,
okay, and here's what תוספות Tosfos says,
okay, the
Okay, so here's
the point.
Okay,
this I love, I love this because of the conceptual point. איסר
issar *Issar* is מתפס בשבועה b'shvua. *mitfas b'shvuah* is what the ברייתא
braisa? *Braitah* says. So איסר issar *Issar* is מתפס *mitfas*, so if
you say I won't eat number two like number one, okay,
that's what the word איסר issar *Issar* means, and
that's a מתפס *mitfas* like we said before. That's אסור asur *assur*
and חייב chayav *chayav*. That's like a classic case when the תורה
Torah *Torah* says ואסר איסר על נפשו ve'asar issar al nafsho. *V'asar
issar al nafsho*, one of the cases in the תורה Torah. *Torah*
that you're חייב chayav *chayav* for is if you do התפסה hatfasah,
*hatfasah*. No question that you're חייב chayav *chayav*. Same point as down
here. But then it says when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* moves on
to say איסור issur, איסר issar *issur issar*, right? And then it
says it doesn't know if that's going to be חייב chayav *chayav*
or not. That's the next language of the ברייתא braisa *Braitah*. What
that actually means is that's two degrees removed. What איסר issar *Issar*
is, התפסה hatfasah? *hatfasah*, you do a התפסה hatfasah, *hatfasah*, you're חייב
chayav. *chayav*. איסור issur איסר issar? *issur issar*, let's say you do
a התפסה hatfasah. *hatfasah* of a התפסה hatfasah, *hatfasah*. Let's say you
say I won't eat number three like number two.
Do you get that?
So this איסר issar. *Issar* is the case in the תורה Torah?
*Torah*. That counts as a שבועה shvua? *shvuah*. You're חייב *chayav*. What
if you did an איסור issur *issur* of an איסר issar *issar*?
What if you said I won't eat number three like number two?
Are you חייב *chayav* or not? So then it depends. How do
you want to understand why you're חייב *chayav* up here? Are you
חייב *chayav* up here because it's כמוציא שבועה מפיו דמי kemotzi shvua
mi-piv dami *k'motzi shvuah mipiv dami*, like you actually said the שבועה
shvua? *shvuah*? If you actually said the שבועה shvua. *shvuah*, then you
could do another derivative of it. Okay, then you're חייב *chayav*. ואם
לאו *v'im lav*, but if you're חייב *chayav* here not because you
said a שבועה shvua *shvuah*, you're חייב *chayav* because it associates with
a שבועה shvua? *shvuah*, but you didn't actually say a שבועה shvua,
*shvuah* on the first case, then the case after would be two
degrees removed and you would be פטור *patur*. Do you get that?
It's very ingenious, right? So let's read that way, I like the
way that reads. הכי קאמר *Hachi ka'amar*. אמר אביי Abaye הכי קאמר
*Amar Abaye hachi ka'amar* and then we've got to move on. מבטא
mifta *Mivta* is a שבועה shvua? *shvuah*. איסר issar
*Issar* in the תורה Torah, *Torah* describes the case of מתפס בשבועה
b'shvua. *mitfas b'shvuah*. I won't eat number two like number one, and
you're חייב *chayav*. That's you transgress, violate a שבועה shvua. *shvuah* in
that case. איסור issur איסר issar *issur issar*, now let's say you
said I won't eat number three like number two. אם אתה אומר
מתפס בשבועה כמוציא שבועה מפיו kemotzi shvua mi-piv... דמי *im atah omer
mitfas b'shvuah k'motzi shvuah mipiv dami*, this is so beautiful. If you
say that the reason that you're חייב *chayav* up here in this
case of מתפס *mitfas* is because it's like you explicitly said a
שבועה shvua *shvuah*, then חייב *chayav*, then you'd be חייב *chayav* even
if you did a derivative of that statement because it's just like
you said the original statement. Okay, ואם לאו *v'im lav*, but if
you're חייב *chayav* here not because you said a שבועה shvua. *shvuah*,
you're חייב *chayav* because you connected it to a שבועה shvua, *shvuah*,
so we're incorporating in here the idea that it's a derivative. It's
not like you actually said a שבועה shvua *shvuah*. You connected something
to a שבועה shvua. *shvuah*.
What did you connect from what to what? Two to one?
Yes, you connected two to one,
and which was not the actual שבועה shvua, *shvuah*.
No, number one, the first apple is definitely your שבועה shvua *shvuah*.
Okay, when you're חייב *chayav* down here for eating apple number two,
right, are you חייב *chayav* for because you made a שבועה shvua
*shvuah* and you said a שבועה shvua *shvuah*, this is a שבועה
shvua *shvuah* and you violated it? That's one way of understanding why
you're חייב *chayav*. Another way of understanding you're חייב *chayav* is because
you said something that's connected to a שבועה shvua. *shvuah*. Okay, so
how do you understand this? If it's like you said a שבועה
shvua. *shvuah*, then saying three is like two, you'd also be חייב
*chayav*, because same idea, it's always like you said the שבועה shvua.
*shvuah*. But if this is just connected to a שבועה shvua. *shvuah*
but it's not really directly a שבועה shvua, *shvuah*, then three is
only connected to something that's connected to a שבועה shvua. *shvuah*.
So what language makes number two only connected but not an actual?
Because you didn't say the word שבועה shvua. *shvuah*. You didn't have
that technical word שבועה shvua, *shvuah*. For something to be a שבועה
shvua, *shvuah*, you need a technical word: מבטא mevate *mivta*, שבועה shvua.
*shvuah*. What makes this not a promise? What makes this not just
סתם *stam*
statement that you're saying? You need something technical to make it a
שבועה shvuah *shvuah*. So number one, you said the word שבועה shvuah.
*shvuah*. Number two, you didn't have a technical word.
All you did was you linked it to number one. Does this
statement become a technical word and it's like you said שבועה shvuah
*shvuah* I won't eat, or does this statement you know, you never
had that technical שבועה shvuah. *shvuah*? But it's just connected to a
שבועה. shvuah? It's a great question. Right? Do we use that word
to say that means you said the word שבועה? shvuah By linking
it it's like you said שבועה? shvuah Or no, by linking it
it's linked, it's not like you said the word שבועה. shvuah. And
the way to test that is are you חייב on number three?
Okay? So I love the conceptual question. By the way, רמב"ם Rambam
has this idea by a ברכה. brachah. רמב"ם Rambam says and people
want to know what the difference is, but רמב"ם Rambam says if
you say a ברכה brachah and I say אמן, Amen, רמב"ם Rambam
says the word אמן, Amen, you know, אמן, Amen, is like I
actually said the ברכה. brachah. כמוציא ברכה מפיו דמי, Kemotzi brachah mi-piv
dami, רש"י Rashi's רמב"ם Rambam says. If you say a ברכה brachah
and I listen and we go by the principle of שומע כעונה,
shome'ah k'oneh, right, רמב"ם Rambam says I'm יוצא yotzei my ברכה brachah
but I didn't say it. Okay? So it's interesting conceptually, you say
who cares, either way I'm יוצא, yotzei, fine, that's a separate discussion.
But you understand that sometimes a word like if I say ditto,
אמן, Amen, right, is like in that word is like I said
the word I needed to say, right? And sometimes I didn't say
the word but I'm associating with something. So here's that question: Is
yes, I'm חייב when I do מתפיס, mitphes, but is that because
this becomes the technical word of שבועה shvuah. or is that just
because it links to a שבועה? shvuah.
So according to this read of תוספות Tosfos which we're going with,
you didn't use a technical word of איסור, issur okay?
But if you had used it, then three would have been the
same.
If you had used it, then that could be that that is
a technical word that means שבועה, shvuah okay? But we're not right
תוספות Tosfos is sort of bracketing that. Okay, רש"י Rashi has a
different read. Let's keep on going. Okay.
ומנא דמבטא שבועה? Uminai d'mifta shvua? How do you know the word
מבטא mifta is a technical word that means שבועה? shvuah דכתיב או
נפש כי תשבע לבטא בשפתים. Dechtiv o nefesh ki tishava levate b'sfatayim.
If a person enunciates to take an oath to enunciate with his
lips. So that becomes a word that means שבועה. shvuah, איסור נמי
דכתיב כל נדר וכל שבועת איסור Issur nami dechtiv kol neder v'chol
shvuat issur or שבועת איסור. shvuat issur. So why do you say
the word איסור issur describes a התפסה, hatfasah. right, מתפיס? mitphes? Why
don't we say it means a technical שבועה shvuah word? אלא מנא
דאיסור מתפיס בשבועה הוא? Ela minai d'issur mitphes b'shvua hu? How do
you know מתפיס mitphes describes a case of התפסה? hatfasah דכתיב או
אסרה איסר על נפשה בשבועה. Dechtiv o asra issur al nafshah b'shvua.
It says to make something forbidden איסור issur with a שבועה. shvuah.
So somehow איסור issur is connected to a שבועה, shvuah. it's not
the שבועה shvuah. itself, it's connected to the שבועה. shvuah. That makes
it a התפסה, hatfasah, it's describing התפסה. hatpasa. So the גמרא Gemara
says מבטא נמי הכתיב לכל אשר יבטא האדם בשבועה, Mifta nami haktiv
l'chol asher yevate ha-adam b'shvua, that a person is מבטא mifta, with
a שבועה, shvuah so it sounds like it's connected to a שבועה
shvuah. but not a שבועה shvuah itself. אלא אמר אביי מבטא שבועה
מהכא. Ela amar Abaye mifta shvua me'hacha. You're right, all those things
suggest it's התפסה, hatpasa not a שבועה shvuah. itself, but we have
another פסוק pasuk that makes it clear that מבטא mifta is a
שבועה shvuah. all by itself and not just through and not just
referring to linking to a שבועה. shvuah.
ואם היו תהיה לאיש ונדריה עליה או מבטא שפתיה אשר אסרה על
נפשה. Ve'im hayo tihiyeh l'ish u'ndareha aleha o mifta sfateha asher asra
al nafshah. Here is the word מבטא, mifta the enunciation of the
lips without at all using the word שבועה. shvuah So you see
that the word מבטא mifta all by itself is a technical word
that means שבועה. shvuah. So if somebody says מבטא mifta. I won't
eat this apple, or I will eat this apple, מבטא mifta is
a technical word that means שבועה. shvua? But איסור issur at least
the way תוספות Tosfos is reading this is not a technical word,
okay? He's not even discussing what happens if you say איסור issur?
I won't eat this apple. It sounds like he's saying איסור issur
is not a technical word. איסור issur refers to a scenario of
התפסה. hatpasa Okay, so that's what אביי Abaye says. איסור issur is
התפסה hatpasa and you're חייב if you're מתפיס בשבועה. mitphes b'shvua, Maybe
we don't know if it's כמוציא שבועה kemotzi shvuah. מפיו דמי or
not, but you're חייב if you're מתפיס בשבועה. matpis bishvuah, That's what
אביי Abaye. says.
Now רבא אמר Rava amar now רבא Rava disagrees. Sorry I skipped
a line. ואילו שבועה לא קאמר, Ve'ilu shvua lo ka'amar, doesn't have
the word שבועה, shvua just says מבטא. mifta במה אסרה עצמה במבטא?
Bimah asrah atzmah bimifta? So מבטא mifta. itself is a language of
a שבועה. shvua? רבא אמר לעולם אימא לך Rava amar le'olam eima
lach I'll tell you מתפיס בשבועה לאו כמוציא שבועה מפיו דמי. mitphes
b'shvua lav kemotzi shvua mi-piv dami. I don't agree with you אביי.
Abaye If you do מתפיס matpis בשבועה, I won't eat number two
like number one, okay, then you would not be חייב. That is
not enough of a language of a שבועה. shvua.
So then how do you read this ברייתא? braisa What is איסור?
issur והכי קאמר, V'hachi ka'amar, here's how the ברייתא braisa? reads: מבטא
mifta is a שבועה, shvua, איסור נמי שבועה. issur nami shvua. איסור
issur, is a technical term just like מבטא. mifta. Okay, you said
איסור issur describes a case of התפסה, hatpasa, I disagree. I think
what the ברייתא braisa is saying is if somebody says מבטא mifta,
I won't eat this apple, it's a שבועה, shvua? and if somebody
says איסור issur, I won't eat this apple, it's a שבועה. shvua.
איסור issur, is a technical term just like מבטא. mifta So what's
the second part of the
ברייתא? Braisa Okay, אסרא דאיסור asrah d'issur so here's where the ברייתא
Braisa says we don't know how to categorize
איסור, issur the nature of the forbidden nature of איסור issur הטילו
הכתוב בין נדר לשבועה. hetilo hakatuv bein neder l'shvua.
It's not clear if somebody uses the technical term איסור, is it
when it says כמוציא שבועה shvua. מפיו... means is it a שבועה
language? Or is it a נדר neder language? Okay. So he says
and it's here we get back to context. It all depends on
context. Okay. Which is funny because before אביי Abaye, was saying context,
now רבא Rava is saying context. הוציאו בלשון נדר נדר, בלשון שבועה
שבועה. Hotzio b'lashon neder neder, b'lashon shevuah shevuah. So if I said,
it all depends on how I say it. Okay. If I say
איסר issar this apple on me, pretend this is an apple. So
that is a language of נדר. neder. Why is it a language
of נדר? neder? Because it focuses on the status of the object.
איסר issar this apple is forbidden to me. If I say איסר
issar I won't eat this apple, then I'm focusing on my act,
and then it's a שבועה. So what רבא Rava says is you
no אביי, Abaye you're saying we're describing התפסה. Hatpasa I don't agree
with you. I actually think התפסה Hatpasa by שבועה doesn't work. התפסה
hatpasa works by נדר neder when it's object related. התפסה hatpasa. doesn't
work when you talk about I can't do this, there you need
the technical term of a שבועה. Okay. So what I interpret the
ברייתא braita to mean is that איסר issar isn't describing
התפסה, hatfasa, I'm sorry, איסר issar is the technical term, just like
מפה mipa is a technical term. So what does the ברייתא braita
mean when it doesn't know exactly what to do with איסר? issar
What it's saying is, is it a technical term of שבועה? Or
is it a technical term of נדר? neder? And the answer is,
it could be either. It depends on the context in which you
use it. If you focus on the object, you made a נדר.
neder. And if you focus on your action, you made a שבועה
with when you use that term איסר. issar Okay. Now היכן הטילו?
Heichan hitilo? Where does the תורה Torah, put it right between a
שבועה and a נדר? neder? Because here's what it says: ואם בית
אישה נדרה, v'im beis ishah nadarah, if the woman made an oath
in her husband's house, או אסרה איסר על נפשה בשבועה, o asrah
issar al nafshah bishvuah, or she made something forbidden on herself with
a שבועה. So the word אסרה איסר, asrah issar, right, two words
before it is the word נדר, neder, and two words after it
is the word שבועה. It's literally right between the words נדר neder
and שבועה. So therefore he says context has to explain what it
means. Okay. So for רבא, Rava, איסר issar is a technical word.
It's a technical word that means either שבועה or נדר, neder, and
it depends how you're using it.
All right. Now let's take a look at trying to figure out
this debate.
Okay. ואזדו לטעמייהו, v'azdu l'taamayhu, they go according to their reasons. דאיתמר,
d'isamar, for it was said: מתפיס matpis בשבועה, if somebody explicitly does
a התפסה בשבועה, hatpasa bishvuah, I won't eat this apple like I
won't eat the first one, and the first one I already took
a שבועה about. אביי אמר כמוציא שבועה מפיו דמי, Abaye amar kemotzi
shevuah mipiv dami, it's out, it's like you said a שבועה, and
now if you violate that, you'll be violating a שבועה of the
תורה. Torah Okay. ורבא אמר לאו כמוציא שבועה מפיו דמי. v'Rava amar
lav kemotzi shevuah mipiv dami. Well, it's not like you took a
שבועה. I mean you shouldn't violate it, but it's not really, does
not have the weight of a שבועה. התפסה hatfasa. works by נדר
neder according to רבא. Rava. התפסה hatfasa. does not work by שבועה.
Okay, because התפסה hatfasa is saying A is like B, it refers
to the object. It's not making an action. If I want to
forbid myself, I have to use the language of a שבועה. Okay.
Now מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you. Here we get a משנה. Mishna.
איזהו איסר האמור בתורה? eizehu issar ha'amur baTorah? This is exactly our
question. What does the phrase איסר issar mean in the תורה? Torah
What does that describe? האומר
הרי עלי שלא אוכל בשר ושלא אשתה יין כיום שמת בו אביו
כיום שמת בו פלוני כיום שנהרג בו גדליה בן אחיקם. ha'omer harei
alai shelo ochal basar v'shelo eshteh yayin k'yom shemeis bo aviv k'yom
shemeis bo ploni k'yom sheneherag bo Gedaliah ben Achikam. Here's somebody who
has taken already took an oath that he doesn't eat,
you know, drink wine or eat meat on his father's on the
יארצייט Yahrtzeit of his father. Here we already have that idea of
observing a יארצייט. Yahrtzeit. כיום שמת בו אביו. k'yom shemeis bo aviv.
And the way this guy observes a יארצייט Yahrtzeit is he already
taken made a נדר neder to make food make wine or meat
forbidden to him on that day. Or somebody else died and somebody
who was close to him and he's taken a נדר neder not
to make wine or meat forbidden on that day, right? Or what
do you call it? Or כיום שנהרג בו גדליה בן אחיקם, k'yom
sheneherag bo Gedaliah ben Achikam, צום גדליה. Tzom Gedaliah.
Of course the funny thing is already he's not supposed to be
eating on צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah because of the תענית. taanis. We'll
get to that. But in addition to the תענית, taanis, he's taken
his own personal נדר neder not to eat on צום גדליה. Tzom
Gedaliah. Or כיום שראה ירושלים בחורבנה, k'yom sherawah Yerushalayim bechurbanah,
he was once visiting Israel and he saw ירושלים Yerushalayim destroyed, and
he took a נדר neder never to eat meat or wine or
meat on that day. And now so that's already an existing נדר
neder he has, not to eat wine or meat, to make wine
or meat forbidden to him on that particular day. And now something
else happened to him today and he's really upset about it and
he says נדר neder to me, you know, whatever, wine and meat
is אסור asur to me today just like it's אסור assur, on
that day of my father's יארצייט Yahrtzeit or that day of צום
גדליה Tzom Gedaliah or whatever it was that other that other day.
So that's classic התפסה. hatfasa He already made something else forbidden to
him, this is as a נדר, neder, the object is forbidden to
him, the wine or the meat. And now he's saying this object
is forbidden like that object. Now it's within a time frame. This
object is forbidden today or at this day every single year. Okay.
So it is time linked but it's still about the status of
the object. So this is classic התפסה בנדר. hatpasa b'neder. This object
is forbidden... Okay, up, אסור, assur it’s forbidden. ואמר שמואל והוא שנדר
בו מאותו היום ve'amar Shmuel vehu shenadar bo me'oto hayom and שמואל
Shmuel explains, that
means when the day you’re associating with, the צום גדליה, Tzom Gedaliah,
the יארצייט, Yartzeit, whatever, you’ve already taken a נדר neder of wine
and meat on that day, and now you’re saying wine and meat
today should be like wine and meat from that day. So that’s
a classic התפסה בנדר. hatfasa b'neder. The first thing is אסור בנדר,
assur b'neder, and the second thing is being associated with the first
thing. Now, okay, that’s התפסה בנדר. hatfasa b'neder. Everybody agrees to התפסה
בנדר. hatfasa b'neder. The debate of אביי Abaye, and רבא Rava is
about התפסה בשבועה, hatfasa b'shvuah, not about התפסה בנדר. hatfasa b'neder. Okay,
like I said, everybody agrees object A like object B that works.
That’s throughout מסכת נדרים Masechet Nedarim is התפסה בנדר. hatfasa b'neder. Alright,
but the problem is is that it says this is the איסר
issar mentioned in the תורה, Torah right? That’s how the ברייתא braita
begins. איזו איסר האמור בתורה? Eizu issar ha'amur b'Torah?
So since it gives a scenario of התפסה, hatfasa and it uses
it to describe the איסר issar in the תורה, Torah. this seems
to be a direct support of אביי, Abaye that the language of
איסר issar in the תורה Torah is a language of התפסה. hatfasa.
You get that? Because it says what is the איסר issar in
the תורה Torah. and describes a scenario of התפסה. hatfasa. Okay, so
let’s take a look. So the גמרא Gemara, says like this,
בשלמא לאביי דמתפיס בנדר נדר מתפיס בשבועה שבועה. Bishlama l'Abaye di'matfis b'neder
neder matfis b'shvuah shvuah. So yes, התפסה hatfasa, with a נדר neder
is a נדר neder and התפסה hatfasa with a שבועה is a
שבועה. Now everybody agrees התפסה hatfasa? with a נדר neder is a
נדר. neder. The real point is not the analogy, the real point
is the ברייתא braita says the word איסר issar in the תורה
Torah refers to התפסה. hatfasa, Okay, yes, it says התפסה בנדר, hatfasa
b'neder, but it basically is a support to אביי Abaye that the
word איסר issar refers to התפסה. hatfasa So that’s what אביי Abaye
says. איסר issar. refers to התפסה, hatfasa. and התפסה hatfasa of a
שבועה counts as a שבועה. Okay, that’s אביי's Abaye position. אלא, Ella,
turning to כ"ף עמוד ב', chaf amud bet, אלא רבא קשיא. ella
Rava kashya. But according to רבא Rava it’s difficult. רבא Rava says
the word איסר issar, means is a technical word, meaning נדר neder
or שבועה. Why is this ברייתא braita illustrating איסר issar, with התפסה?
hatpasa, For רבא Rava that’s not what איסר issar, is. איסר issar
is a technical term. So אלא רבא קשיא אמר לך רבא, ella
Rava kashya amar lach Rava, רבא Rava would tell say to you,
תרץ מהכי, taretz meihachi, read the ברייתא this way. איזו איסר נדר
האמור בתורה, Eizu issar neder ha'amur b'Torah, not איזו איסר האמור בתורה.
Eizu issar ha'amur b'Torah. No, we’re not describing the technical word איסר
issar in the תורה. Torah? He does say what’s the case in
the תורה Torah? of a נדר, neder, alright, meaning he downplays it.
It’s just yes, it’s describing התפסה, hatpasa but it’s not describing התפסה
to describe the technical term איסר issar? in the תורה. Torah The
technical term איסר in the תורה means נדר neder or שבועה. Okay,
that’s not what it means. What it just means is, what is
the forbidden nature of a נדר האמור בתורה? neder ha'amur b'Torah? האומר
הרי עלי שלא אוכל בשר ושלא אשתה יין כיום שמת בו אביו
כיום שנהרג בו פלוני. Ha'omer harei alai shelo ochal basar shelo eshteh
yayin k'yom shemet bo aviv k'yom sheneherag bo ploni. ואמר שמואל והוא
שנדר בו מאותו היום. ve'amar Shmuel vehu shenadar bo me'oto hayom.
Okay, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what’s the reason? אמר קרא, amar kra,
because the verse says, איש כי ידור נדר לה' עד שידור בדבר
הנדור. Ish ki yidor neder l'Hashem ad sheyidor b'davar hanadur. So you
have to say when something is forbidden, it has to be forbidden
like something that’s already forbidden as a נדר. neder. Alright, so meaning
רבא's Rava saying the word איסר here does not mean the technical
term. איסר the technical term means נדר neder or שבועה for רבא.
Rava. What the גמרא, Gemara what the ברייתא's saying for רבא Rava
is what is the classic נדר neder in the תורה? Forget the
word איסר. What is the classic forbidden nature, which is not the
technical term איסר, what is the classic forbidden nature of a נדר
neder in the תורה? It’s when you say A is like B,
or excuse me, B is like A, and A is already forbidden
to you by a נדר, neder, based on the פסוק, pasuk, right,
כי ידור נדר. ki yidor neder. The נדר neder has to link
already to a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, to something that already is
vowed. Alright, so basically what you have is like this, alright.
I hope this is not getting too technical, okay.
You have the word in the
תורה איסר, ואסר איסר על
נפשו. אביי Abaye says what that means is it describes a case
of התפסה. Okay, and he says התפסה is כמוציא שבועה. That’s what
the word האיסר ha'issar applies. Maybe for him there is no technical
term איסר, okay. רבא, Rava, for רבא, Rava, what this means is
it’s a technical term, technical you say term, okay, like מצווה mitzvah
is a technical term, you say if you say like איסר I
won’t eat,
then it’s a שבועה.
If you say איסר this apple is forbidden, forbidden, then
it’s a נדר. neder. Okay, so what you don’t know is what
would אביי Abaye, say about איסר? For אביי, Abaye right, so that’s
what the For אביי *Abaye*, is איסור *Issur*? So if the person
says איסור *Issur*, whatever, I won't eat, for אביי *Abaye*, you don't
know what he would say. Okay, is that a technical term or
not? Does that mean שבועה *shvua* or not? We don't know for
אביי *Abaye*. For רבא Rava *Rava*, if you say a התפסה *hatfasa*,
okay,
right, for רבא Rava *Rava*, if you do a התפסה *hatfasa*, if
you say I
won't eat
number two like number one, רבא *Rava* says you are not חייב
*chayav*. Okay, he says התפסה *hatfasa* is not כמות שבועה מפי עצמו
דמי *kemot shvua mipi atzmo dami*. Okay, so this is like what
happens if they hold, you know, in each other's case, right?
Okay, so that's their, that's the debate of אביי *Abaye* and רבא
*Rava*, whether התפסה *hatfasa* is כמות שבועה מפי עצמו דמי *kemot shvua
mipi atzmo dami*. We quoted a whole, what do you call, ברייתא
*braita* that said that used the word איסור *issur* to refer to
התפסה *hatfasa*, right, which is exactly what אביי *Abaye* did. It used
the word איסור *issur* to refer to התפסה *hatfasa*. And what רבא
*Rava* says is, is that the ברייתא *braita* was not using the
word איסור *issur*. You misunderstood the ברייתא *braita*. It wasn't really talking
about the איסור *issur* word in the תורה *Torah*. The ברייתא *braita*
was just telling you that a classic נדר neder *neder* is a
התפסה *hatfasa*. Now I want to say one more thing about that,
why a classic נדר neder *neder* is a התפסה *hatfasa*. Even forget
when I say apple number one is like apple number two. Let's
just start with apple number one. If I want to say this
apple is forbidden to me as a נדר neder? *neder*, what's my
power to do that? Okay, the most, the classic term of the
word נדר neder *neder* in the משנה *mishna* at least is the
word קונם *konam*. קונם *konam* is when I say קונם *konam* this
apple, this apple is קונם *konam* עלי *alai*. קונם *konam* is a
sort of variation of the word קרבן *korban*. Okay, any, the classic
language of a נדר neder *neder* refers to something that is of
a, that is already forbidden through a speech act. If I say
this apple is forbidden to me by נדר neder, *neder*, by קונם
*konam*, this apple is forbidden to me, I'm already doing a type
of a התפסה *hatfasa*. I'm already suggesting that there's a concept of
a קרבן *korban* out there and I'm making this apple like that
קרבן *korban*. Classic נדר neder. *neder* is התפסה *hatfasa*, עד שידור בדבר
הנדור *ad sheyidor bedavar hanadur*. That's not just a scenario of נדר
neder. *neder*. My ability for my speech to change the status of
something, right, because I'm change, where do I get the ability through
my words to change the status? That derives from the whole world
that I can make something a קרבן *korban*, I can make something
הקדש *hekdesh*. I have that power of speech in other areas to
sanctify something to the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. So when I make
my apple forbidden like a קרבן *korban*, it's derived conceptually from that
world of קרבנות *korbanot* and בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* and all those
things. So that's why classic נדר neder *neder* is דבר הנדור davar
hanadur? *davar hanadur*. My power derives from associating my power of speech
and objects that I already can make forbidden. Okay, that's why everybody
agrees that התפסה *hatfasa* works by נדר neder *neder*. The question is,
does התפסה *hatfasa* work by שבועה *shvua*? Because שבועה *shvua* is by
calling upon God to witness something. It's not by statuses of objects,
right? So therefore saying A is like B and whatever, like what
difference does any of that make? It's not about the status and
the sanctifying, as it were, of an object. It's about calling on
God, so that's why there's a debate whether התפסה בשבועה *hatfasa bishvua*
works. All right, so that's basically where we are. Everybody agrees התפסה
*hatfasa* works by נדר neder. *neder*. That's classically what נדר neder, *neder*
is. And there's a debate of אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava* whether
התפסה *hatfasa* works by שבועה *shvua*, because conceptually שבועה *shvua* is very
distinct from נדרים nedarim *nedarim*. All right, I hope I'm not making
this too complicated. I hope I'm making it clearer rather than more
complex, I don't know. Okay, moving on. All right, so now the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this. Now let's just finish up this ברייתא
*braita*. כיום שמת בו אביו פשיטא *kiyom shemeis bo aviv peshita*. So
obviously like if a person already took a נדר neder. *neder* on
the יארצייט *yahrtzeit*, you can make some something forbidden on a different
day like it was on that day. כיום שנהרג בו גדליה בן
אחיקם אצטריכא ליה *kiyom shenehreg bo Gedalia ben Achikam itzricha lei*. And
the חידוש *chiddush* is if you say that this is forbidden to
me like it is on צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah, *Tzom Gedalia*. Because
צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah, *Tzom Gedalia* is not a דבר הנדור davar
hanadur. *davar hanadur*. The reason we don't eat on צום גדליה Tzom
Gedaliah. *Tzom Gedalia* is because either you know, it's like it's a
rabbinic fast day. So how can you make something אסור assur, *assur*?
If I say this apple is forbidden to me like apples are
forbidden on יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*, okay, that's not a
נדר neder. *neder*. Apples aren't forbidden on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom
Kippur* because of a נדר neder *neder*. I have to associate it
with something that's forbidden because of a נדר neder. *neder*. So if
I say this meat is forbidden to me like it's forbidden on
צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah *Tzom Gedalia*, meat is not forbidden on צום
גדליה Tzom Gedaliah, *Tzom Gedalia* by virtue of a נדר *neder*. So
therefore how does that work? So סלקא דעתך אמינא *salka datach amina*
I would have thought כיון דלא נדר נמי אסור assur *keivan dela
nadar nami assur*, since if you didn't take an oath, it would
also be forbidden on צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah, *Tzom Gedalia*. So צום
גדליה Tzom Gedaliah *Tzom Gedalia* is not something that's forbidden by virtue
of an oath. צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah, *Tzom Gedalia* is forbidden by
virtue of the fact that it's a תענית Taanit? *ta'anis*. So כי
נדר נמי לא הוי עליה איסור Ki nadar nami lo havi alei
issur, *ki nadar nami lo havei alei issur*. Okay, if you take
a, so even if what I did was, I really feel terrible
about גדליה *Gedalia*. So now it's not enough for me that there's
a תענית Taanit, of צום גדליה, Tzom Gedaliah I add a נדר
to it. And I say, you know what, נדר on צום גדליה,
Tzom Gedaliah all meat and wine or whatever, all food is אסור
to me בנדר b'neder on צום גדליה. Tzom Gedaliah Okay, so now
have I also made the stuff forbidden
as
a, you know, as a דבר הנדור? davar hanadur. Does that layer
take place on top of the already forbidden nature of the fact
that already it's a תענית? Taanit And the relevance would be, a,
if I eat on צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah am I also violating
a נדר? And the other relevance would be, if I say, food
and meat and wine is forbidden to me today like that נדר
I made about צום גדליה, Tzom Gedaliah, okay, like the way it's
forbidden on צום גדליה, what if that נדר didn't take effect, then
the meat and wine today isn't relating to a נדר, it's relating
to a תענית, Taanit, but a תענית isn't a נדר. It has
to, it only gets its weight by relating to a נדר. Okay,
so the גמרא says like this. כיון דאילו נדר נמי אסור, Keivan
d'chilo nadar nami assur, since if you didn't take a נדר it
would also be forbidden. כי נדר נמי לא הוי עליה איסור, okay,
so even when you took a נדר it does not maybe, perhaps
it doesn't get the weight on צום גדליה of being also forbidden
as a נדר. והאי לאו מתפיס בנדר הוא, V'hai lav matfis b'neder
hu, and now when you're saying this day is like צום גדליה,
you're not connecting it to a נדר, you're connecting it to a
תענית, but that's not a נדר. קא משמע לן Kamashma lan that
you are connecting it to a נדר. Okay, because why? Because even
though צום גדליה was already אסור, you could add another layer of
איסור, a forbiddenness. Okay, there is a whole interesting debate of רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot how much you really can do that. Is
it only because צום גדליה is דרבנן? d'rabbanan? So since צום גדליה
is דרבנן, d'rabbanan, you're able to add on to it a נדר
which is דאורייתא. d'oraita. Maybe it wouldn't work by יום כיפור. Maybe
if you said on יום כיפור all food is אסור to me
בנדר, b'neder, we would say the principle of אין איסור חל על
איסור, ein issur chal al issur, right? You can't have one forbidden
status take place on top of another one. But because צום גדליה
is only a rabbinic, you know, fast day, you can make the
stuff forbidden to you also by virtue of a נדר. And once
you've done that, then when you say today is like צום גדליה,
you're linking it to something that's not just a fast day but
also is a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur. All right? People more or
less getting this? All right, so the basic point is:
classic נדרים nedarim work by associating it with a דבר הנדור. That's
your speech power to change the status of objects. So when you
make an object forbidden, it's because you're associating it either with a
concrete or abstract other thing that is forbidden through a speech act.
So classic נדרים is rooted in the idea of התפסה, of associating
a status of one object to another object under the דבר הנדור.
And everybody agrees to that. The question is, does that work by
שבועה? Because classic שבועה is calling on God to testify. So if
I say, I won't eat this apple like I won't eat that
apple, is that like I said a שבועה? Is that like I
took an oath? Okay, so there's one question of what are your
technical terms for שבועה. One technical term is שבועה, I won't eat
this apple. One is מבטא, mifta I won't eat this apple. Is
איסור I won't eat this apple a technical term? That's not clear.
רבא says that is a technical term. אביי ignores the question. And
then the other question is, is התפסה actually something that works by
שבועה? All right, I know it's already a little over but let's
just read the next line because it'll go, you know, just two
more minutes and it'll get us a little further into the דף.
daf. Okay.
ואף ר' יוחנן סבר לה להא דרבא, V'af Rav Yochanan savar lah
l'ha d'Rava, ר' יוחנן Rav Yochanan holds of רבא that מתפיס matfis
is a technical term. דכי אתא רבין אמר ר' יוחנן, D'ki ata
Rabin amar Rav Yochanan, מבטא לא אוכל לך, mifta lo ochal l'cha,
if somebody says מבטא I won't eat your stuff, or איסור לא
אוכל לך, issur lo ochal l'cha, שבועה. Either way is a שבועה.
Okay, so there you go, it's a technical term. איסור is a
technical term just like מבטא is.
Okay, I guess we will stop here. It's a shame, but I
don't want to rush through the next part. So we will pick
up from here.